welcome back to am Northwest our
next guest always has unique antique
collections to share and he says this
item is a distinctive one for you to
collect we welcome back antique appraiser
Gary Gman Gary great to see you again
oh absolutely appreciate it okay I'm
going to step to the side here because we
need to see some of these you're you're
fine right where you are I look so thin
Behind These but tell me about this is a
type a Japanese block art it's called J
it's Japanese wood block prints and they
they started you know back in the 700s
got and they we did basically black and
white and the idea of a wood block print
like the name implies yeah is that the
artists would make a painting or drawing
and then it'll be transferred to a a
piece of paper and then it'll be put onto
wood blocks so depending on what you
were doing you may need up to eight wood
blocks that could wow cuz each one would
be a different color yeah so if you
look that's a lot of work this right
here this down here if you can see those
down or not um those
date to about the uh late
1700s and the the idea of these woodblock
prints they figured out this Printing
and so it was an inexpensive way they
could make and re reproduce art yeah and
so the theory was they called it the
yukoh E there'll be a test on this so we
remember that which meant floating world
and they loved having beautiful women
sumo wrestlers actors there'd
be scenes of of inside
of a castles where you wouldn't normally
get to see life inside temples all the
and then even like tourist likee pictures
and they were done and sold to the
public in Japan um and they were cheap
they're like they said they'd be about
the same as the price of a bowl of noodles
so at the time it would be equivalent
like $2 to5 today well I guess price of
noodles are $10 now but um you get the
point wer they were accessible for
people and they weren't considered
necessarily High art but they were wildly
popular so you get the old ones like
that and you look at how many colors
there are or even like this one here if
you've only let look up here cuz the
camera's better this is later this is the
mid um 1800s this is a later actual print
of it though by a guy named Hiro shigi
and if you've never heard of woodblock
print artist hiros Shiki is probably the
one you would recognize the most he was
extremely popular extremely popular to
the West what happened in the art World
in Japan and the key is when the end of
the what they called the Ido period
which was from the 1600s up until the
1860s um it was like this and it was all
very restricted you had to use certain
colors certain sizes you had to go
certain things and they had sensors that
would go around and check wow what happened
in the 1860s is it Japan open to the
west and all of a sudden there was this
influx of Western Art and all these wood
blocks came to the US and Europe and
they were stunned they had never seen
anything like this right so as cultures
go they flip-flopped this was high art
then in Europe and they thought in Japan
it was cheap art and Japan liked the
oil paintings and so then they went that
direction that's interesting so that's
how it all evolved and so you've got
like these here here shigi they has the
depth of color yeah his stuff is fantastic
and then um this is also I forget the
artist on this particular one but gives
you idea themes where do you find some
of these were these estate sales someone
who really a collector you can find
them this particular collection yeah I
had a lady whose parents were moving to
assisted living in Bandon Oregon and
she says we have about 25 of them wow so
she brought 35 and then she said oh I
found more and brought another 35 so I
have 70 of them I'm going through when I
came to the woodblock she ended up they
would they would take the wood blocks
usually use Cherrywood okay and they would
line them up with notches so that each
block would fit so when you printed it
together you ended up and it would range
in from the multicolor this is more of
a modern one here let me hold this one
you can hold it and that's actually two
colors black and blue and that's all
there is so you can see you can get
saturated depth of color and there's a
lot of creativity that can happen oh my
gosh that's gorgeous well Japan moved up
to the uh Western World you know their
uh Society got caught up to the Western
World and so they had what they called
the hanga the there was the SOI hanga
and the shin hanga art movement which is
the 20th century this is the ones I love
the most are the more modern ones like
this the style is completely different
completely different and um they have
same themes there'll be scenes of
um different cities different places
there was a fellow named and I didn't have
one but a had fellow named and bra just
jumped out of my head no worries who did
who taught Christianity using them in
Japan wood block prints so you'll find um
his prints are done in red black on
white paper and it's all different Bible
stories done in oh wow okay so tell me
about this one in the front here you pull
that out you pull it out well I brought
this because it almost looks Southeast
Asian but it' be from the southern parts
of Japan and it's just a difference of
color you can see the range of a rainbow
color and a whole whole different look
I love it and so you can get the
more mono monoch chromatic colors
or you get this one of my favorite
artists is this guy here okay
oh wrong one sorry but I like this one
a lot and you can see they got the snow
um the whole fing C and it's a specific
town a specific place that you can find
the ones I what I was going to say is
these two here closest to you Helen are by
a guy named um SED Koshi sedo and Koshi um
is is wildly collected and
um if you can get his cats
I don't have any of his cats but he did
a whole bunch of cats that are crazy
they're fantastic oh wow and they bring
a couple thousand dollars yeah these um
these remind I these are like so
familiar so we know we've seen this style
before we have and it fits a lot of
people who are in the mid-century modern
decorating these fit perfectly yeah
absolutely they also fit in classic Styles
because they're they're they're kind
of Timeless but the color's always Rich
they're always such great moods and the
idea that they can do it with a stack of
wood blocks it's so crazy now the this
it is changing because it used to take
you know the drawing would take the artist
uh the time to make it and there'd be
like four to six helpers who would do
the carving because each color know a
different different different the whole
process is kind of incredible what would
something like let's say this one or
this one over here cost they're they're
actually fairly affordable s's a
big artist um if you can find his
work his Landscapes and Interiors
are in the $500 range okay uh three
to six depending on which one it is the
cats go for everybody wants the cats and
the dogs and so they're anywhere from
$15 to $2500 wow but you can find like
this one here I think he's quite Charming
I don't know quite who he is I have to
do a little bit more homework on who
he is and what's the purpose of it the
artists I know but the you know what
the subject matter really this is really
fun I haven't seen these before or in
at least in such such a long time I like
the idea because they are affordable
and yet uh and the process is is
historic yeah thank you so much Gary
appreciate it we're going to put all the
information on our website at k2.com
we'll be right back with more am Northwest
don't go away